Inspired by real events.
In the winter of 1940 the
British and German fought in Norway.
The goal was to gain control over the
iron ore supply from Norway.
There was fighting between German bombers
and British fighter planes.
- Are there any casualties? Strunk?
- No.
- Schwartz?
- I have been hit in the elbow.
Hauk?
- Hauk!
- Hauk is dead.
Sergeant, take care of the airman's
wounds. Disinfect and bandage it.
I will go and find out
which way to go.
Am I going to die?
I'm not going to die right?
The wound is in the elbow, airman. In the elbow.
Ready?
Why did he fly on? Everything
said we have to turn back.
It's allright, it's useless to worry about it now.
Lieutenant? Lieutenant!
Lieutenant!
- Schopis!
- I'm down here!
Under the snow!
What happened?
I fell down there.
That's what happened.
Excellent.
- Joseph, your book.
- What do you have there?
I waited for six hours
at Alexanderplatz in Berlin.
Finally, Hitler came by.
It's his autograph.
Biscuits, chocolate, sausage,
sauerkraut and beer.
- Beer?
- You never know, Lieutenant.
Yes. You are right.
What do we do now?
We march to the coast,
find our army and go to war again.
And Officer Hauk fell for his country.
"In time of need, where others despair, heroes rise
from seemingly innocent children -
- filled death defying
determination and icy cool head."
"But..."
"It's almost always necessary
to call the genius to the plane."
"The Hammer of Fate that would pound others
into the ground -
- suddenly meets with steel..."
It's as if Hitler was speaking to me.
To us.
Don't you understand?
We were alone against three enemy planes,
and we survived.
And we shot one of them down. It's
Minus 20 degrees, and we're not freezing.
Turn off the light.
We need the battery.
We can't go anywhere.
Look out!
Strunk!
- The sled is too heavy!
- Release the belt.
- What?
- I say again! Release the belt!
Oatmeal.
Do we have water?
Strunk, fire up the oven.
Norwegians are thorough people.
- Shit!
- What?
Only two.
Can you hear it?
I hate this fucking white.
I hereby declare this shithole part of the German Reich.
- Stop!
- Who's there?
Stop! Don't move! Who is there?
Beg your pardon?
English?
Who are you?
- A British officer and his airman.
- What are you doing here?
Our aircraft's been shot down.
About two miles from here.
- And who might you be?
- We are german pilots.
We've been shot down too.
Well...
- Come in
- Lieutenant?
Thank you.
I suppose there's no chance for a spout of tea.
Lieutenant Horst Schopis.
Sergeant Wolfgang Strunk
Airman Josef Schwartz.
Hi. My name is Captain Davenport,
and this is my gunner Smith.
- Where did you spend the night?
- In the plane.
- And you?
- In a snowcave.
A hunting cabin I presume.
Room for everyone.
- Why don't Smith and I sleep over here?
- No.
- Those are our beds.
- Your beds?
- Yes.
We've all just arrived here
how can they be your beds?
- It is best you sleep over there.
- Why?
- Listen. We were friendly. We invited you in.
Indeed you did, but this is a Norwegian cabin.
Who do you imagine the owners would
want to share with? You or me?
If we are in a german occupied country, it will be me.
And sooner or later this will be a part of Germany.
Now go over there and sit!
I'm a British officer and I have no intentions
of taking orders from you.
It is five o'clock and you are now officially
prisoners of the Third Reich.
I order you to go over there!
- Fuck the Third Reich.
- Hold your mouth!
- Never say that again!
- These are exceptional circumstances Lieutenant.
- We need to work together.
- We will work together Captain.
But you will be our prisoners.
Lieutenant shouldn't we shoot them?
- No.
- English please.
- Why not?
- We are not hottentots Schwarz.
- English please.
- Quiet!
But they would kill us if they had the opportunity.
I'm sure of that.
Well then go.
- I should shoot them?
- Yes.
Yes. You have my permission.
Well then go.
You're gonna shoot me?
But they yould also be useful as hostages
And they can lay a false trail in the snow,
when we leave here.
- So I should let them live?
- Yes.
I think that would be the best.
You ought to be holding a rattle for children,
not a gun.
Hands on the bed. I'm not asking gentlemen!
Hands on the bed!
We're unarmed. Un Armed!
- Very nice. We'll put the stove on. (?)
- I'll have that back if you don't mind.
We take care of the fire, we keep the lighter.
That was a present from my father on my fifteenth birthday.
He gave it to me for good luck.
Good luck Captain?
Look around.
When we leave I will give you back the lighter.
You have my word.
No. I keep the lighter,
and whenever you need it you come to me.
- I'm not going anywhere.
- Why are you making problems from such a little thing?
It's not a little thing, and as far as I can see,
you're the one making the problem.
Bloody Germans.
Away!
Quiet!
I want to make a few things clear.
You're prisoners of war.
And you'll stay with us in this cabin
until the weather improves.
Tomorrow we will go to the sea and from there
you will be taken to a prison camp.
- Is that clear?
- I think he's made himself perfectly clear.
Don't you Smith?
Sure put to the points sir.
This is the British side,
and this is the German side.
You will ask permission every time
you want to leave the British side.
If not, we will shoot you.
Is that understood?
Yes.
Well. In that case, in accordance
with the Geneva convention -
- i believe we're entitled to a bed,
three meals a day -
- and sporting facilities.
Do not worry.
You will be treated fairly.
I'd hardly call your poilicy
of sharing fair.
Under the circumstances many would say
putting a bullet into your head is fair.
You get the same food we get.
Bed and shelter?
You get the same shelter we get.
And for sporting facilities...
May I introduce you to the
beautiful Norwegian countryside!
Any questions?
Where's the toilet?
Toilet is out there on the left.
Here. Toiletpaper.
That's not toiletpaper.
Smaller pieces.
Annoy them anyway you can Smith.
Provoke them.
Make them feel stressed and insecure.
- Got that?
- Yes sir.
Strunk will go with you.
And bring back more firewood.
What was your name again?
Me Smith.
One more time.
Me Smith. You...?
- What's your name?!
- Strunk.
So Skunk.
How do you like Norway?
Didn't think so.
Me neither.
Is it true you can't eat other than sausages?
Hey skunky!
How come you're not cold?
Maybe you're too fucking stupid to feel cold.
Is everything allright?
Ye.
Help him!
Go!
We must fix your bandage.
Strunk!
- Big bum don't speak a word of English.
- He doesn't speak German either, Smith.
- Who's side are you on sir?
- Shh!
- Is it bad?
- No no.
- The wound just have to be cleaned.
- Ooh. Nasty wound. Well infect-
You're not to cross that line unless I give you permission!
Whatever you say.
It's nothing.
Just trying to help.
I'm a British Officer in Her Majesty's Royal Marines, and Smith here is my airman.
We refuse to eat off the floor.
- Why make a problem out of this?
- This?
We want to eat at the table. Like you.
Is that a problem?
No. Not at all.
Grab it.
- Take a seat sir.
- Thank you Smith.
Well... enjoy.
- It's good.
- This? Hope you're fucking joking.
- Makes strong.
-?
- German soilders can march for days on this.
- Is that right? Germans don't eat much.
- And how come you've invaded Poland?
Wasn't Germany enough?
- Hold your mouth!
And you. Go to your bed.
- Now you want it?
- No.
I don't want a nazi to eat it.
You should teach your airman
some manners and discipline.
That's none of your business.
Captain Davenport...
You are right.
This is none of my business.
Besides. Maybe my observer was
following my orders.
Why can't we sit and
talk like civilized people?
Just talk.
A conversation?
About what?
Anything.
Okay. Well what about politics?
Not a good idea.
Cars?
Yes. Germany is known to build
the best cars in the world.
Well certainly the most boring cars in the world.
British cars have elegance and style.
- Yes. But they break dow all the time.
- So what?
Would you marry a woman because she was reliable
and always serve dinner at seven o'clock?
- Well I wouldn't hold that against heer.
- But where would that leave sensuality and adventure?
Without the unexpected
people become bored.
How do you Germans feel about Jesse Owens?
Black fellow beat the shit out of your best men at the Olympics.
- He was a great athlete and deserved to win.
- For God's sake guys!
We're stuck in this shithole talking about petty matters -
- when all we want to do is get
the hell out of here and back to our girls.
Right?
- What?
- Girls.
You do have girls in Germany don't you?
Tonight I was supposed to be on a date with Sheila.
The new bartender back at the airbase.
Blue eyes, flaming red hair -
- and a figure, that would give a fellow a?
They all tried their luck.
But not on your life.
- But you had your luck with her?
- Indeed. I won her.
Well actually she won me.
See I'm a local darts champion
three times in a row.
And when Sheila turns up I orderd me a pint.
She says to me:
"Smith, I like you, and if you can
beat me in darts tonight I'm yours."
- And uh. Did you beat her?
- She beat me three times in a row.
Fair and square.
And the day before we left she slides
this small piece of paper across the counter.
Just like that.
What did the note say?
"Can't wait for your game to improve"
"Come and see me as soon as you get back."
Love Sheila.
Then you shot us down.
What about the big lug over there?
Who's the woman in his life?
Strunk has a family.
Three kids and a lovely wife.
- Does he ever speak to her?
- Sergeant Stunk makes his family very proud of him.
He works for the family business.
2000 workers.
And then he even volunteered
for the German Luftwaffe.
- Why did he volunteer?
- To serve his country.
And Hitler junior, who's the love of your life?
Your mother?
His mother is dead.
Well what about you?
Have you got anyone waiting for you?
- Haven't we all?
- I certainly have.
And talking about women,
time for washing the dishes now.
- You and Smith will do it.
- You didn't answer.
I did.
You will do the dishes now.
- Oh well I'm afraid we cant.
- Why not?
The kitchen's on the German side.
Your compass contains alcohol.
It might kill the infection.
Don't they teach you anything at the German Luftwaffe?
Of course, but then we would
not have no compass, Davenport.
So our position is 62 degrees
0 minutes and 33 seconds.
- So we are...
- Four kilometres.
- Planning our trip tomorrow?
- Yes.
I think you'll find that West is that way.
- No, that way.
- Two kilometres...
Well you should have checked your compass
before you smashed it.
West is in that direction
and I can prove it.
- Your scarf is of silk?
- Of course it is.
May I borrow it?
Permission to cross the border?
The silk makes the needle magnetic.
Well Lieutenant you were right.
Nice little compass.
Basic knowledge in the German Luftwaffe
I need to take a piss.
Oh come on! Where would I run to?
You're not gonna win this war mate.
What the fuck kind of sausages do you eat?
Anti-freeze?
You win the pissing contest, Dunk.
Congratulations.
Strunk? Strunk?
2 o'clock. It's your turn.
No!
No! No.
- Josef...
- No!
I dreamt the British have eaten me.
They laughed as they ate me.
- They are sleeping.
- I don't trust them Lieutenant.
You don't need to
We are armed.
We bomb British ships and
shoot British ariplanes.
- Why can't we just shoot them both?
- They are useful as hostages.
Lieutenant?
Where's your pistol?
In my hand.
Time to get up.
We leave in half an hour.
We'd rather stay here
if you don't mind.
Do you need a mirror?
Why not?
But I take the razor after.
We're somewhere here.
We will go up this way. Across the mountain.
Have you seen the weather?
For God's sake man this is untamed wilderness.
We're out of food and there's hardly any wood left.
- We leave now
- Lieutenant. I have a suggestion.
- Why don't we go our separate ways.
- No.
Why not?
- There are rules of war.
- Yes why are you Germans so obsessed with rules and regulations?
You will never understand. That is why Germany
is great and the British Empire is crumbling.
- Crumbling? Nonsense, the Empire is doing fine.
- Fine? Wake up Captain!
Come on! This way!
Strunk, I cannot go on.
Get up.
Lieutenant!
Stop!
Strunk!
Lieutenant!
Follow the trail.
Over here!
We must go back!
Go back to the cabin!
Let's face it.
We're all going to die here.
Lieutenant, why didn't we turn around?
I don't understand!
- All the other airplanes have...
- That's enough airman!
But we should have turned back. Why didn't we?
We had an order.
A made a decision.
- But...
- There's nothing more to say about it!
How on Earth do you expect us to survive?
We have the bed, supports,
We can take it from the floor and the wall.
You! Help him.
I know what we can eat
- We're seriously gonna eat moss?
- It's tasty and full of vitamins.
Food rule nr. 1: If it's full of
vitamins it tastes like shit.
It's good.
Not bad.
A steak would be nice.
We could try hunting.
- You don't like youp either.
- I said the soup is okay you stupid sud (?)
All I'm saying that it would be nice with a steak.
I suppose old Adolf is a vegeterian too.
- I'm not a vegeterian!
- Then how come you're so skinny?
- Stop!
So Smith are you really a champion dartplayer?
- Two bloody days. (?)
- No he's not.
Okay give me three bullets you stuffed
marching penguin and I'll prove it to you
Stand up.
Yes, do it Schwarz!
Now point at one of Josef's buttons.
- What?
- Point at one of Josef's buttons
This one.
Don't move.
You were lucky..
Don't move!
You cannot do this three times.
- You were right Lieutenant!
- You did that on purpose!
You should have seen your face.
Not to put too fine a word in it, but your soup has given me the runs.
- What?
- Permission to shit?
I neet to go to the toilet.
- Very good, Smith.
- Thank you.
Captain Davenport.
Thank you.
Reindeer.
Come and shoot them.
Reindeer! Come and shoot them!
Fuck.
Fucking Hell!
Ten to fifteen reindeer
right in front of the fucking cabin!
I know.
They've gone now. Fuck.
Hey, Josef...
I have to say.
Chapter two war a little rough on my arse.
Bloody idiot you've done it now.
I kill you.
.
- Get out of the way!
- Josef! Give me your weapon.
- Out of the way. Out of the way!
- I said weapon down.
- You are dead..
- I strongly suggest you apologize, Smith.
- Apologize for what?
You are not completely yourself.
Give me the weapon.
- He has insulted the Fuhrer!
- You are a proud german airman!
German Luftwaffe prides itself
on order and discipline.
- Do not abandon that now corporal.
- Get out of the way!
- You are dead!
- The Lieutenant your commanding
officer has given you an order.
You need to obey it.
Now listen to your commanding
officer and put down your gun.
Do you really want to disobey your leader?
I did not give you permission
to cross that line, Captain.
Weapons on the floor!
Now!
And slide them over there!
Nice work Smith.
Right. You, over there.
Are you taking us prisoners?
- That's right.
- Well in that case according to the
Geneva Convention we are entitled to...
- I know, I know.
- Yes you know.
But do you also acceppt it as your responsibility?
Right. It's time to change places.
- Please consider Josef's condition.
- He'll be fine over there.
Allright leave him be.
Have Strunk carry all the would-be weapons
over to out side.
Now.
Do it.
And the axe.
I've got a few questions.
You already have taken most of Europe.
Not England but most of Europe.
How does that feel?
I don't know
I'm just a pilot.
Think harder.
- I feel sad.
- Than why did you do it?
Orders.
When do you think Hitler will be satisfied then?
When he's taken China?
- Maybe.
- What the fuck does he want with China?
- They speak Chinese over there for Christ's sake!
- I guess you're right.
One last question: What makes you think
you have the right to invade everyone?
- Maybe we are just kile you.
- I'm sorry you've lost me there.
- England invaded the whole world exactly the same way.
- We did not!
What about India?
What about all your colonies?
You sailed away with a gun and a Bible in
your hand and took whatever you wanted!
- That is the whole reason we're here.
- You're over your head mate!
- Am I? We are here to protect the Norwegians from you.
- What?
You want the land and more importantly
you want what is in it.
- What the fuck would we want with this place?
- You don't know? Raw materials.
Raw materials for your industry.
Your ships, your planes, your bombs.
That is why we both are here.
History, Robert.
We all want raw materials.
There's nothing to eat.
What will you do about it?
We'll get some more moss.
I'll go out and shoot a norwegian reindeer.
Satisfied?
- Take Strunk with you.
- Why?
Because that's an order.
Get up Skunk. Get up.
Here. You'll need an extra gun for hunting.
Take this one too.
- I don't think that's a goo idea.
- I didn't ask what you think. Just do it.
This is where the reindeer were
I told you.
Go on.
Axe please.
Excellent.
Help me!
Excellent?
- I told you.
- Spare me your notable remarks.
What are you doing?
- Not a very sporty gesture.
- This is war, not a silly game in your country club.
Keep it for all i care, just help me here!
Tell me why is it so damned important
for you to be in control all the time?
Because that's how it is.
Am I right?
Why?
Look at me!
Nice shooting.
- Did you just speak?
- Yes.
Why the hell didn't you
say anything before then?
You never say anything interesting.
What the Devil is the matter with you?
- I'm a failure.
- Nonsense. Keep pushing.
Yes I am.
- What on Earth are you talking about?
- I'm a lousy pilot.
- Well I'm an excellent pilot and you shot me down.
- On my first flight I made a plane crash.
Three people died.
I was sent three months in prison.
But when the war broke out
they gave me a new chance.
On the next flight I
crashed into a hangar.
I lost a man on this trip,
and look at Josef.
Please don't.
I'm sorry.
How come you have volunteered Strunk?
I mean you're almos forty.
- You earned a lot of money. You didn't have to.
- It was my duty.
Oh come on!
Would you like to run a
company with 2000 men?
Paperwork, responsibility
and long hours?
- No fucking way.
- Me neither. So I volunteered.
And then you met me.
Get going.
Strunk! The beam!
Do something!
Yes.
- Put the gun down!
- You put the gun down!
- How did he get it?
- It's a little complicated.
I'm willing to lower my gun
if you do the same.
And end up in a german prison camp? No, fucking thank you!
- Do it Smith.
- We need to work together.
We forget the guns, make a cease-fire and...
and live like one big happy family?
Trust me on this one Smith.
Right. On three.
One. Two.
Three.
- Well that's it.
- Yes. When you've dropped your second gun.
Do it Smith.
Right. That's that.
We have to skin her don't we?
Sir you've gone hunting back home.
Yes but we have people to take care of this kind of thing.
But what do you think they do?
Get me a knife.
Oh come on! It can't be that hard.
What?
First we take the head off.
- You like cooking?
- I've never tried it before.
Never?
No.
You never helped your mother?
Actually she never cooked either.
But it feels good.
Do you smell it?
It's gangrene I'm afraid.
Are you sure?
I'm sorry.
God!
We must amputate his arm and get him to a hospital.
How do we do this?
With the axe.
We need to heat water.
Take whatever you can use for wood.
The beds floor whatever.
Smith get some snow.
Then we disinfect the axe and then...
We must stop the blood.
- Can you help me with the jacket?
- Lieutenant! I have found something!
It's dried meat.
- But why hide it there?
- To stop you germans from finding it.
Can we have a drink now?
Good idea.
Ready?
- Josef?
- Wake up!
We found some schnaps and we have a drink competition with the British!
The one who empties the bottle first.
You must participate.
Cheers Josef.
- Up Liverpool.
- Come on get it down you! More!
We must win!
You have to drink more!
- Yes yes yes we're winning.
- Don't you drink?
- Come on Smith they're winning they're winning!
- Drink on the Fuhrer!
Drink for Germany!
Germany anthem
Germany Germany
above everything
above everything in the world
When, for protection and defence, it always
takes a brotherly stand together.
- Want me to do it?
- Thanks.
But no, thanks
Did we win?
Yes yes. Yes yes we won.
- Everything's good.
- What are you doing?
Do you mind?
What should we do with the arm?
I don't know.
We get rid of it.
We can't it belons to Josef.
What would he want with it?
It's a bit of a pickle really.
We have to do something.
We could wrap something around it and -
- bury it. Outside.
Yes.
We will bury the arm
and make a small ceremony.
Perhaps Josef would like to be present.
Yes.
Maybe it's bet to... wait.
Oh for fuck's sake.
Come here you.
Can we please have a drink now?
NORWEGIAN MILITARY CAMP AT STRYN
...the rest are in good shape.
OK let's talk tomorrow. Thank you.
I came across a burned out German aircraft.
Here at Heilstuguvatn.
So that's where they are.
And the crew?
I don't know.
We must look for them tomorrow.
Your turn Smith.
Tell us -
- how you impressed this lovely sheila.
- No way.
- Come on.
- Sheila.
- Sheila, Sheila, Sheila!
Allright! I showed her me cock and she fainted.
That often happens when you're
not used to wearing strong glasses.
Come on Smith.
Tell us.
How did you do it?
Okay. I sang to her.
You sang?
I got up on the bar and I sang to everyone.
And that did the trick.
- And what did you sing?
- "Over the Rainbow".
- I heard she liked the "Wizard of Oz".
- I'll be damned.
And can we hear it?
- No way.
- Come on.
No.
- You can't sing.
- Yes I can.
- So come on. Sing!
- Sing!
Sing! Sing!
Sing! Sing! Sing!
I need to piss.
No contests this time please.
- Liar!
Here you are.
Well I could...
Somewhere over the rainbow
Way up high
There's a land that I heard of
Once in a lullaby.
Somewhere over the rainbow
Skies are blue
And the dreams that you dare to dream
Really do come true.
Someday I'll wish upon a star
And wake up where the clouds are far
Behind me.
Where troubles melt like lemon drops
Away above the chimney tops
That's where you'll find me.
Somewhere over the rainbow
Bluebirds fly.
Birds fly over the rainbow.
Why then, oh why can't I?
Bravo!
And you Captain?
Do you have anything for us?
Actually I do.
And I have no hesitation in
saying it will completely -
- outshine your
brilliant performances.
So what is it?
Close your eyes.
Now open your eyes.
Where did these come from?
Well actually I was saving them
till we saw the sea.
But now seems a more
appropriate moment.
I can see the sea through
these little tubes of delight.
What?
I can see the sea through
these little tubes of delight.
MY BATTLE
ADOLF HITLER
Gentlemen it's been
a pleasure and an honor.
If you could do something else
what would that be?
- Stupid question
- Why?
What if the company burned down
and your parents said to you:
"Listen Stookey there's no future here.
Go do something else."
Why should I talk to you about this?
You are a man without principles.
- I have lots of principles. Want to hear one?
- No
Do whatever make syou happy.
What about responsibility?
What about the responsibility to be happy?
Raise your left arm.
You see? You always do what you're told.
No one told me to volunteer for the army.
No one.
But the only reason you did was
to get away from the family business.
It was the choice of the less evil for you.
So now I'm asking:
When will you do something
that makes you happy?
Goodnight.
What happened?
- It's gone?
- You had gangrene.
- You would have died.
- It still hurts.
Look at me!
You gave your arm for your Fuhrer!
He would be proud of you.
Here eat some chocolate.
We have plenty.
Shall we go home now?
Yes we're going home.
I think you and Smith should leave now.
Are you sure?
Josef is better but we will
only slow you down.
- I have a suggestion.
- Yes Smith?
I climb the hill and look for a better way.
You stay here and make some kind of sled
for Josef and then we'll all go.
- Do you know how to ski Smith?
- I tried it once with my uncle when i was a nipper Sir.
Ah an expert. Excellent.
- I go with you.
- Good.
It's wonderful here.
It certainly is.
One could stay here until the war is over.
Maybe you should.
But you'd probably miss home.
My wife left me. A week ago.
She just left me with my...
with my best friend.
I'm sorry.
I wanted to impress her and -
- I went too far.
And...
Here we are.
She'll be back old man.
They've just left Germany.
So I suppose you're serious about staying here?
We could put one pair of skis underneath.
With nails.
What do you think?
- Yes!
- Why did you say yes?
- I won.
- You did not.
- I always wanted to be a painter.
- Of course you have.
Then go for it.
- What about money?
- Go to Paris and paint the tourists.
Get a cheap room and become a bohemian.
Girls like that.
- There is a war on.
- Yes and no Trunk.
- My father will be very dissapointed.
- Maybe not.
You don't know my father.
It seems he doesn't know you either.
Beautiful.
See it's easy if you go that way.
Here's the plan Trunky.
We'll go back, get the others,
then we'll walk slowly that way down the mountain.
We look for signs. If we're in british territory
then you go further South.
- And the other way around.
- Good idea.
I think we better go.
I'm starting to like you.
Go? I'll show you what
downward ski is all about lazy.
- Am I going too fast for you?
- Out of my way you sauerkraut!
Rule, Britannia...
Strunk?
Wake up!
Stupid English.
Strunk.
Hands up!
Don't shoot. I'm british.
What? British?
Search him.
It's okey
You're safe.
You're safe now.
Stop!
Hands in the air!
Drop you guns! Drop you guns!
I'm a british Officer.
No!
Get up!
Why?
Someday I'll look up his family.
Got a few things to tell them.
We have plenty to talk about
when we are down the mountain.
Let's go.
Gome on move!
So you shot each other down
on the 27th of april.
- Answer.
- Yes.
And you and airgunner Smith slept in the plane.
Yes.
And the next day you arrived
at the same cabin as the germans.
- Yes.
- Is it not a strange coincidance?
Yes.
And in the cabin they kept you as prisoners of war
because the yhad weapons and you had none.
That's right.
But you had a luger
and we found another one in the cabin.
- Yes.
- So the one thing I don't undestand is why...
Why didn't you shoot them?
This information goes straight to the Norwegian Army
and from ther to your commanding officer.
I'm not an expert, but the way I see it
they will think that you are traitors.
Both of you.
The Lieutenant would like to give back something.
- You want something Lieutenant?
- Yes.
- It belongs to Captain Davenport.
- It's just a lighter.
- And now you want to return it?
- Yes.
Why do you have his lighter?
I took it from him.
Was that all Lieutenant?
- Yes.
- Come with me.
Lieutenant Horst Schopis
tells the same story.
They kept you es prisoners bla-bla-bla -
- but you know something. I don't believe either of you.
And if I find the slightest evidence
that you have been collaborating I'm coming after you and..
Listen to me you twisted cheese eating gnome!
While you've been sitting on your arse down here waiting -
- for the sun to shine we've been struggling to survive!
In a remote cabin with some Germans!
And we did survive! Most of us!
And now I have my lighter back.
And that is the end of the matter.
Anything else?
No.
Good.
Let's go Smith.
Move!
This way.
Horst Schopis spent seven years
as a prisoner of war in Canada.
A few days after returning to England -
- Davenport and Smith
flew a mission over Trondheim.
They were shot down again.
Davenport was captured and spent
the rest of the war in a German prison camp.
Smith died in the attack.
Strunk is buried at the
war cemetery in Trondheim.
Josef spent the rest of the war
in a prison camp in Canada.
In 1977, Horst received a call
at his home in Munich.
It was Davenport.
He invited Horst to London.
A little later the
two former enemies met.
As friends.
Translation: Eff